[Music]
when the 20th century was young Henry
Ford summed up the attitude toward
Choice by saying people could buy one of
his cars in any color they wanted as
long as it was black but times and
tastes change very quickly today as we
approach the 21st century choice and
change have become the dominant
characteristics of our society virtually
every product in every industry offers a
variety of choices to appeal to the
Public's changing taste and needs when
the insurance industry followed suit the
credential became a leader in providing
choices now the credential is
celebrating a product that represents
choice at its best Val variable appre
able life began its 11th year in
1995 and the future of choice looks
better than ever from its beginning
variable appreciable life has been
viewed by the credential and by the
industry as an Innovative and exciting
product a Viewpoint which our clients
obviously shared since Val quickly
became the credentials most successful
product this video is the first in a
series about Val in this and subsequent
programs we hope to build on the
excitement that launch V 10 years ago
show you how the significant features of
vow work and see how those features mean
benefits which can help your clients
toward their Insurance and financial
objectives for example in this program
we're going to review some of the V
Basics to help you understand and use
this contract most effectively you'll
see how the product has evolved over
time and look at the most recent
enhancements and modifications to our
current practices which are designed to
keep Val and attractive and sound
product and we have three brief role
plays to demonstrate specifically how to
explain the ultimate premium change to
clients now while Val is still a
relatively young product it already has
an impressive history in the late 70s
High interest rates led to the growth of
Universal Life Products but as interest
rates began to decline many consumers
began to look for a different way to
safeguard their financial future they
still wanted the security of a permanent
life insurance but they want it in a
product that offers individuals the
opportunity to react to their changing
financial needs and obligations as well
as the changing economic climate Val
combines some of the best features of
traditional whole life universal life
and variable life offering choices that
work for a wide range of client needs
for example premium flexibility is one
of Val's most important features B
clients can select a premium payment
schedule that fits their current budget
and a adjust payments as their
situations change or they can choose a
higher level premium option and be build
for the same premium for the life of the
contract in either case clients can make
additional payments to help their policy
values grow and each client decides how
his or her premium dollars after certain
deductions of course should be allocated
among investment options clients
essentially customize the investment
portion of their policy to take into
account their personal levels of risk
tolerance as well as their needs and any
external changing economic conditions
clients can also take advantage of vs
withdrawal and Loan privileges which
give them access to the contract funds
they have built up periodic reviews of
these and other Val features ensure
you'll be able to give your clients the
information they need as they make the
financial choices that are right for
them full details about all of Val's
features are contained in updated
marketing and training material created
as part of Val's 10th anniversary
promotion one of the aspects of Val to
which you should pay special attention
is the way the product has evolved
credential continually refines Val to
keep it fresh competitive and
financially solid when Val was first
introduced the series fund portfolio of
investment options contained only five
choices subsequently several investment
options including the real property
account were added to the prol life
version verions of Val when we
introduced Val 886 we adopted our
current practice of no longer deducting
sales charges once we had received five
annual premiums this practice was
applied to enforced policies as well as
to new business it effectively reduced
the price of the policy the present
product Val 88 included the zeroc coupon
Bond options and is issued by credential
instead of prol life as you can see Val
is a dynamic product
the credential is constantly adding
portfolios to the series fund to give
our clients more investment diversity
regardless of what changes are made to
the series fund or to other aspects of
Val our goal is the same to provide
value to our clients and to manage the
business to make sure the credential is
here in 100 years to make good on our
promises and keeping with this goal
we're introducing several new features
to the product effective May 1995 first
first we were adding two more investment
options to the contract a gross stock
portfolio and a small cap stock
portfolio the grow stock portfolio is
complementary to the common stock
portfolio which is managed on a value
strategy a small capitalization stock
portfolio will provide clients with the
opportunity to invest in smaller
companies and will be based on the S&P
small cap 600
index the other new feature of Val is a
revision to the current process we use
for the ultimate premium change
calculation a distinctive feature of
Val's design is the modified premium
structure and how it supports the
guarantee against laps the modified
premium has always been an attractive
feature because it means clients can
purchase about 50% more permanent
insurance for each dollar of their
initial premium than could be bought
under a comparable level premium
policy when a valve policy is sold we
must explain to clients that we charge a
relatively low initial premium but that
would reserve the right to charge a
higher premium later the time for
changing to a higher premium is the
policy anniversary following age 65 or
the 7eventh policy anniversary whichever
is later for the prolif vals it is age
65 or the 10th policy anniversary
whichever is later this is called the
premium change date in 1994 with the
first Val contracts beginning to reach
their premium change date we implemented
a process to determine a new scheduled
premium which would guarantee the death
benefit under the contract and would for
many clients be lower than the maximum
schedule premium found in the contract
this lower premium could be as low as
the initial scheduled premium for
contracts reaching their premium change
date on or after May 1st 1996 we will
only guarantee the lower premium for one
year at a time but we will only give an
annual guarantee practically speaking we
do not expect to actually change the
premium retaining the flexibility to
change it allows us to maintain smaller
but still adequate and conservative
reserves the modified process will be
reflected in the May 1st 1995 perspectus
and will apply to all Val contracts
which reach their premium change date on
or after May 1st
1996 the current process will continue
to apply to those contracts which reach
their premium change date prior to May
1st
1996 at this time it's necessary to tie
in another aspect of Val's premium
flexibility the way we monitor premium
payments to check whether we have
received all due schedule premiums on a
valve policy we have a device called the
premium account this allows us to check
each month and compare all scheduled
premiums due to date against all
premiums actually paid for this purpose
we consider a withdrawal as a negative
premium payment for for example if a
client paid his or her $1,000 scheduled
premium wind do but then withdrew $1,000
the next day the premium has in effect
not been paid for the death benefit
guarantee to be in effect the premium
account balance must be at least zero
that is the premiums paid accumulated at
4% must at least equal the scheduled
premiums due also accumulated at 4% if
those two match exactly the premium
account balance is zero if the paid side
exceeds the due side there is a positive
balance and of course if the due side
exceeds the paid side there is a
negative balance a client can always
bring his or her premium account up to
Zero by paying any missing premiums plus
4% interest incidentally the 4% interest
is not lost to the policy owner but
remains in the contract fund now let's
see how the premium account operates in
the premium change process the whole
purpose of the premium change process is
to determine a new premium for the
premium account the guarantee that the
contract will not lapse will be based on
the payment of the new lower premium
when do we intend to update the premium
account by the lower amount but reserve
the right to change it payment of the
lower premium net of withdrawal will
guarantee the contract a year at a time
let's look at an example using an
illustration from the May 1995
perspectives this is an illustration for
a male age 35 preferred $100,000 valb
variable death benefit in a state using
a 2% State premium tax the illustration
does not include waiver a premium the
initial scheduled premium is
$894,000 ious assumptions on growth
rates the maximum ultimate premium in
this case is
$472 61 as shown in the footnote for a
gross rate of
0% this means that if this client Pays
His premiums from age 35 to 65 and earns
0% gross then his premium will increase
to the maximum pretty much as he would
have
expected for earnings of 4% the contract
fund has grown such that there is a
small reduction in the scheduled premium
the footnote based on an assumed growth
rate of 8% gross shows that the
recalculated maximum premium is about
$3,260 but the second lower premium is
8946 this is the same as the initial
premium and again consistent with what
you would expect if the theoretical
scenario laid out in this illustration
actually came to pass then this client
would get a bill for
$894,000 % net as of the premium change
date he will see his maximum premium
reduced and Will Bill at or very close
to his initial premium whether it is to
explain the addition of new portfolios
to the series fund or to explain the
premium change date this latest stage in
the evolution of Val gives you two new
opportunities for discussion with both
new and enforc
clients choice and change many consumer
products they can reflect merely passing
fancies but to Consumers with
sophisticated taste and needs they
represent flexibility versatility and in
economic terms
affordability these are the principles
that will continue to make Val and you
successful Pat Edwards is making a sales
call with a potential firsttime
credential client Ellen March Pat has
conducted a thorough needs analysis and
gathered information about Ellen that
indicates a Val policy is the most
suitable option to meet her financial
objectives using illustrations she has
customized for Ellen Pat has already
gone over many of the features of Val
and is about to explain the scheduled
premium amounts and the premium change
date there are a couple of important
features about Val that I'd like to go
over with you Ellen they concern the
contract
guarantees as we had discussed the
initial scheduled premium for your vow
policy is lower than the premium would
be for a regular whole life policy if
you pay the scheduled premiums when they
are due and don't make any withdrawals
then the policy is guaranteed not to
lapse due to poor investment results yes
I remember you saying that and I think
you said there's a grace period too what
was that you have 61 days after each due
date to pay the scheduled premium the
initial scheduled premium continues up
to age 65 actually it's the policy
anniversary following your 65th birthday
at that point the premium can go up what
can it go up too well the most the
premium can go up is shown here on this
illustration it will also be shown on
your policy and is called the ultimate
premium your ultimate premium is
$3,800 3,00
,800 that's quite a bit higher than
$780 but you said it can go up does that
mean it might not go up that's right
this is the maximum your premium could
be the actual scheduled premium will
depend on a number of considerations one
your policy's value at the premium
change date we don't know how the
Investments you've chosen are going to
perform two we also don't know how much
premium you're going to pay in over the
next 30 years or so or what withdrawals
you might make and three we can't be
sure exactly what our charges for things
like mortality and expenses will be all
of these things will influence your
policy value so when we get to the
premium change date we'll look at your
policy at that particular point in time
and we'll calculate a new premium for
you the new premium can never be more
than this maximum shown here now if this
is the most it could be what's the least
good question Ellen it cannot be less
than the initial premium so if I
understand correctly the premium after
age 65 can't be less than the initial
premium but can't be more than the
ultimate premium that's right okay
according to this my present premium
would be $780 a year what would have to
happen so it wouldn't change okay let's
assume you pay all your premiums when
they're due don't make any withdrawals
and earn somewhere in the neighborhood
of six or 7% net let's also assume
assume our current level of charges
stays the same in that case we'll send
you a bill which will show two premiums
a new maximum scheduled premium and a
second lower one the lower premium would
be at or near the present $780 a year
and that $780 will guarantee my policy
payment of that premium will guarantee
that your policy cannot lapse due to
poor investment results until the next
policy anniversary we reserve the right
to change that premium
but it can never be more than the new
maximum premium shown on your bill we
don't anticipate changing your premium
and we would only consider changes for a
whole class of policies not just yours
as an individual I think I understand
what else do I need to
know today is May 18th
1996 Bob is a 67-year-old preferred
issue holder of a credential $100,000
Val B variable death benefit contract
which he took out when he was 60
presedential rep Hal carpenter has been
servicing Bob's insurance needs for
about six years although he did not sell
Bob the Val policy originally he is here
today because Bob's policy has reached
its premium change date Bob I know that
ever since I took over your policy we've
gotten together once a year just to go
over your annual statements I don't know
if you remember but last year when I was
here I said your premium was due to
change this year do you remember that
not really well on this anniversary you
will have reached what your contract
calls the premium change date the bill
you're going to be getting will look a
little different I thought this would be
a good opportunity to go over the
premium change in a little more detail
so you'll understand the bill when it
arrives is that okay sure let's just
look at your
policy right now for your $100,000
policy the scheduled premium that's the
premium we've been billing you has been
$315 a month in the policy it said that
the premium could go as high as
$492 see right here
$492 does this mean you're getting ready
to charge me
$492 not at all when you took out the
policy we were able to charge you the
low premium the
$35 and guarantee the policy by
reserving the right to change the
premium to $492
if we had to at a future
date and and I've got good news for you
it won't be
$492 how much we're actually going to
have to charge you depends on how well
your contract's done your contract fund
right
now see this amount here is just over
$220,000 which is pretty good in fact I
did a little research and over the last
seven years you've paid all your
premiums when due according to this
statement you've earned on average 8.9%
on your money so on your premium change
date we looked at your policy with those
facts in mind and have come up with two
new premiums
two next month on your new bill the $492
maximum will be gone it no longer
applies your new maximum premium from
now on would be
$458 and because of your contract's
performance your monthly premium will be
$315 that's a relief
why do I even need to go through this
premium change date thing than if it
doesn't change because it does change
for some people when we quote you this
new maximum premium basically we have to
take into account several things we have
no idea how your Investments are going
to perform until the policy matures or
what sort of charges we're going to have
to make what mortality rates are going
to be or what our expenses are going to
be in that same time period being an
insurance company we have to make some
conservative estimates on what all that
might be not just for you but for all of
our policy holders we guarantee that
from now on we could never raise you
more than this maximum amount to keep
your policy in force but
frankly since we think that's going to
be more than is needed to keep your
policy in force given any reasonable set
of circumstances we've determine the
lower amount should be sufficient so we
will bill you at the $315 monthly
premium
and if I pay that amount each month we
guarantee your policy won't lapse due to
poor investment performance prior to the
next
anniversary you said my contract has
been earning about 88.9% on average what
if my average goes down is is that when
I'd start paying that higher amount the
premiums not figured simply on the
performance of your Investments there
would have to be many years of negative
returns across the whole spectrum of
Investments for us to consider changing
everybody's premium not just yours for
the type of policy you have we reserve
the right to change the premium if we
need it to let's say all investment
results within the series fund as a
whole went very badly for a number of
years then it's possible we'd consider
charging more than
$315 but even if we did it could never
go beyond your new maximum the
$458 at any future time so what you're
saying is in my case it isn't necessary
to change now right right while it could
change we do not expect that it will
what if I paid less than what you're
asking me to paying that premium
guarantees that your contract cannot
lapse due to poor investment performance
on a year-by-year basis if you don't pay
that premium but you don't make any
withdrawals either the policy still
stays in forc provided there's enough
money in the contract fund right now
you're fine it's possible that if you
earn favorable investment results over
the coming years and don't pay any more
premiums your policy would stay in force
but when you do that you're relying on
investment performance to keep your
policy in force in that case your
individual investment performance is a
consideration and your policy could
lapse unless you made up the missing
premiums and brought your fund back up
to an acceptable
level I get it how long before I see the
First new statement
it's September
1995 Bob is a 67-year-old preferred
issue holder of a $100,000 credential
valb varable death benefit contract
purchased in 1988 when he was 60
presedential agent Hal carpenter has
been servicing Bob's insurance needs for
about 6 years although he did not sell
Bob the Val policy originally
is here today because Bob's policy has
reached its premium change date as usual
Bob I just wanted to keep in touch with
you on your anniversary date the last
time we met I mentioned your policy
would be due to change this year you're
going to get a new premium Bill next
month your present premium is $315 a
month but on your policy it says that
once you had the policy 7 years or
reached age 65 whichever is later it
could go up as much as
$492 oh no no you mean it's going to go
up to
$492 not at all the good news is your
premium is not going up your premium
change date came up we looked at your
account and estimated a new premium but
because your policy has done very well
your premium hasn't changed it will stay
$315 a month continue to pay us $315 a
month and your policy is guaranteed not
to lapse regardless of investment
results are you going to change it
somewhere down the line we will never
change your $315 premium if you don't
pay it your policy could lapse if the
contract fund goes below a certain level
but as long as you pay your premium and
take no withdrawals your premium isn't
going to change and your policy will not
lapse note that although the situation
is very similar to the second role play
there are two important differences
because the premium change date occurred
in
1995 first there is only one premium
quote
and second there is no year-to-year
guarantee